Guide to the Pilot Mills Company records, 1890-1971 RL.11842
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pilot Mills Company records
1890-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11842
9 Linear Feet 5 boxes; 4 oversize folders; 1 volume
The Pilot Mills Company was a cotton textile mill based in Raleigh, North Carolina and founded in 1892. Files in the collection include correspondence (1892-1918), legal records (1892-1922), financial records (1890-1971), plans and blueprints (1890-1971), printed material (1906), and other records relating to the mill's construction and equipping, its ownership, and its financial operations. Persons represented include co-founder William Holt Williamson.
Historical Note
The Pilot Mill Company was one of two textile mills in Raleigh that produced gray goods (unfinished cotton). The site was purchased in 1892 by James and William Williamson and the first mill building was built that same year. The 1892 building was built with bricks made by prisoners at the North Carolina State Prison (then located where the NC State Fairgrounds currently stands). The 1892 Building housed the mill's spinning and weaving functions. In 1910, Pilot Mills expanded into a new building, built that year, next to the first building. The Williamson family operated the mill until 1918, after which several owners operated it until its closure around 1982. The mill was then used as a warehouse until its purchase for redevelopment in 1988. It was listed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1989.
[Source: Capital Area Preservation, Raleigh, "The 1910 Building at Pilot Mill," accessed April 28, 2020]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Pilot Mills Company records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1983.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises correspondence (1892-1918), legal records (1892-1922), financial records (1890-1971), plans and blueprints (1890-1971), printed material (1906), and other records relating to the Pilot Mills Company, based in Raleigh, North Carolina, and its construction and equipping, its ownership, and its financial operations. There are four folders of oversize materials, chiefly blueprints and plans; there are also several volumes. Persons represented include co-owner William Holt Williamson.
Cotton manufacture -- North Carolina; Cotton textile industry -- North Carolina; Textile factories -- Design and construction; Textile industry -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; Raleigh (N.C.) -- History
- Pilot Mills Company records, 1890-1971
  - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1894 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1902 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1903-1918 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1893-1897 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1898-1904 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1907-1908 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1910-1915 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1916-1919 (Box 2)
  - Legal papers, 1920-1922 and undated (Box 2)
  - Legal papers: Contracts and specifications for construction and equipment, 1895-1908 and undated (Box 2)
  - Legal papers: Certificate of Incorporation, 1906; By-Laws, 1912 and undated; Articles of Agreement, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Legal papers: Contracts and specifications for construction and equipment, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Financial statements and reports, 1893-1899 (Box 2)
  - Financial statements and reports, 1900-1917 and undated (Box 2)
  - Financial papers: Stockholders file, 1907-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Preferred stock certificates, nos. 1-11, 1901-1906 (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Purchase orders, correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Invoices, bills, receipts, 1890, 1892 January-October (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Invoices, bills, receipts, 1892 November-1893 March (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Invoices, bills, receipts, 1893 April-June (Box 3)
  - Financial papers: Invoices, bills, receipts, 1893 July-1894 and undated (Box 3)
  - Copper printing block of William H. Williamson, circa 1890s (Box 4)
  - Copper printing blocks of Pilot Cotton Mills, circa 1890s (Box 4)
  - Building plans, 1890s (Box 4)
  - Printed material, 1906 and undated (Box 4)
  - Volumes (3), 1918, 1960s (Box 5)
  - Loose volume (Volume L:7029)
  - Oversize materials (Oversize-folder A)
  - Oversize materials (Oversize-folder B)
  - Oversize materials (Oversize-folder 1)